<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE data [
	<!ELEMENT history ((data)+)>
	<!ELEMENT data ((year,des,color)+)>
	<!ELEMENT year (#PCDATA)>
	<!ELEMENT des (#PCDATA)>
	<!ELEMENT color (#PCDATA)>
]>



<history>
		<data>
				<year>1800</year>
				<des>The Ojibwa Mide Ceremony that is a part of the Medewewin or Grand Medicine Society recorded their migration from Eastern Canada, the great Salt Sea, through the Great Lakes to the Prairies.  They departed their Great Town on the Salt Sea because of sickness and death.  They first moved to Moneaung (Montreal).  After a long period they moved to Lake Huron.  Again after a great period they moved to Boweting (Sault Ste Marie).  </des>
				<color>#0D0D0D</color>
		</data>	
		
		<data>
				<year>1802</year>
				<des>Indian maps convey much information where European documents fail.  The People draw maps in scale to travel time rather than an impractical mile scale.  A difficult river route occupies more space than easy ones of the same length, because it takes more time to travel.  French Canadian travel distance is calculated in night’s sleep where as the Metis, Coureurs de Bois, and Voyagers modified this system as pipes smoked.  The Ojibwa of Rainy Lake have a thriving business in the sale of wild rice to the fur trade.</des>
				<color>#1A1A1A</color>
		</data>	

		<data>
				<year>1804</year>
				<des>Peter Grant (1764-1848) a Northwest trader at Lac La Pluie wrote it is customary in winter for the tribes to break up into single family units.  This is a precaution necessary to their very existence.  They choose a particular hunting district and no other person will encroach upon it without a special invitation.  If they discover a beaver lodge they mark the situation and no other person would attempt to destroy it without permission.</des>
				<color>#262626</color>
		</data>	

		<data>
				<year>1805</year>
				<des>Lewis and Clark noted the Kalispel People (ear drop People) in northern Idaho.  They also visited the Kamiah People whom they called the Chopunnish People that numbered 800.  They are in fact a group of Nez Perce People.  The Klikitat a Shahaptian tribe who originally lived in Washington along the Lewis and White Rivers were noted by Lewis and Clark as living on the Yakima and Klickitat Rivers.  Lewis and Clark met the Klumaitumsh People who originally lived in Grays Harbor, Washington.  </des>
				<color>#333333</color>
		</data>	

		<data>
				<year>1806</year>
				<des>Meriweather Lewis met with the Blackfoot and made it very clear that the Americans came to establish peace between Indian tribes.  He stated the Americans intended to trade guns and ammunitions with the Shoshones and Nez Perces, mortal enemies of the Blackfoot.  Lewis and Reuben Field each killed a Blackfoot warrior.  This caused the Americans to be classed among the enemy of the Blackfoot, resulting in a 30 year standoff with much blood shed.  Most Americans dont appreciate the significant of this statement.</des>
				<color>#404040</color>
		</data>	

		<data>
				<year>1807</year>
				<des>A 42 man American Expedition into northwestern Montana is killed to the last man by the Blackfoot People.A trading post is built at the junction of the Yellowstone and Big Horn Rivers by Manuel Lisa a Spaniard from St. Louis.  He traded guns and ammunition with the Crow who were at war with the Blackfoot.Lisa retired in 1811 to the lower Missouri River area, founding the Missouri Fur Co.In case of famine any one may abandon his district and seek a better hunt on his neighbor's territory.</des>
				<color>#4C4C4C</color>
		</data>	
		<data>
				<year>1808</year>
				<des>June 14: At Cayoosh Flat (Lillooet, B.C.) the St'at'imc Nation debated to kill the (II)-Simon Frazer Party or to meet them in peace.  A consensus was finally reached for peace.  They welcomed the party into camp and provided them supplies.Following a naval victory over the Portuguese on December 24, 1808, negotiations were started developed into the opening of the first East India Company factory at Surat in 1613. It later grew to encompass much of western and central India.</des>
				<color>#595959</color>
		</data>	
		<data>
				<year>1810</year>
				<des>This year is remembered as the decline of the moose in Ojibwa Country some say as a result of over killing for the fur trade.  An Ojibwa band north of Lake Superior began to diminish in size.  By 1829 they are down to singular families that is better able to sustain themselves with small game.  Records of starvation among the People began to appear after this date. leaving the whole of this frontier exposed to the inroads and depredations of the enemy</des>
				<color>#666666</color>
		</data>	
		
		<data>
				<year>1811</year>
				<des>The battle of Beaver Dam on Twenty Mile Creek is summarized as follows; the Cognauga fought the battle, the Mohawk got the plunder and Lieutenant Fitzgibbon and De Haren who arrived with the regulars after the day had been won, claimed the credit.  The American General Peter B. Porter wrote disgustedly; the truth is we have had an army at Fort George for two months, this army lays panic-struck, shut up and held in by a few hundred miserable savages.</des>
				<color>#737373</color>
		</data>	
		
		<data>
				<year>1812</year>
				<des>A spokesperson of the Pillager band of Chippewa (Ojibwa) said he did not wish to mingle among quarrels between white men, nor did he intend ever to be guilty of breaking the window glass of the white man's dwelling.The War of 1812 was a 32-month military conflict between the United States of America and the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, its North American colonies and its Indian allies, but involved no boundary changes.</des>
				<color>#808080</color>
		</data>	
		
		<data>
				<year>1813</year>
				<des>The Native style of forest warfare is very different from the European line and siege type of warfare.  The Natives shamed Colonel Proctor into making a stand at Moravian Town on October 5, 1813.  Tecumseh and his men did the fighting and not Proctor and his Red Coats as claimed by some historians.  General Tecumseh, (1768-1813) the Shawnee war chief gave his life; Proctor saved his by flight.  This shameful action by the Red Coats discouraged the Peoples resistance in the Michigan and Lake Erie Region.</des>
				<color>#8C8C8C</color>
		</data>	
		
		<data>
				<year>1814</year>
				<des>The treaty of Ghent maintained the status quo with the Americans agreeing to restore all possessions rights and privileges to the People  The demand for clearly defined Indian Territory however is again frustrated.The Bannock People destroyed John Reids Trading Post on the lower Boise River Idaho.Resistance however continued in the upper reaches of Lake Huron and in Wisconsin. its North American colonies and its Indian allies</des>
				<color>#999999</color>
		</data>	
		
		<data>
				<year>1815</year>
				<des>The traders at India discovered how Maple Syrup is stored for later use.  The hyderabad made miniature barrels out of one piece of wood, sides and ends one piece, the interior being burnt out through the bung hole.  If the barrels are buried three feet deep it will keep a year or so. The history of Anglo-Indian relations was determined by the ... Two major events in the eighteenth century changed Britain's position in India.To organise this effectively meant that parliament had to regulate the company's </des>
				<color>#A6A6A6</color>
		</data>	
		
		<data>
				<year>1816</year>
				<des>This is recorded as the year without a summer.At San Francisco 300 Indians are dying annually from measles, cholera, smallpox and the Spanish disease of syphilis.The Year Without a Summer, a peculiar 19th century disaster, played out during 1816 when weather in Europe and North America took a bizarre turn that resulted in widespread crop failures and even famine.The weather in 1816 was bizarre. Spring came but then everything seemed to turn backward, as cold temperatures returned. The sky seemed permanently overcast. </des>
				<color>#B2B2B2</color>
		</data>	
		
		<data>
				<year>1817</year>
				<des>John Ross a Metis born October 3, 1790 of a Scottish father and a Cherokee mother died August 1, 1866.  He worked on the Cherokee Council this year to settle which lands the Cherokee would or would not have.  Later he himself was forced to a reservation,The United States acquired the Dakota’s through the Louisiana purchase .November 27:US soldiers attacked a Florida Indian village and started the first Seminole war. Andrew Jackson invaded Florida with 3,000 men forcing Spain to cede the land to the United States.  </des>
				<color>#BFBFBF</color>
		</data>	
		
		<data>
				<year>1818</year>
				<des>Manavadar (Bantva-Manavadar) becomes a British Protectorate, a Princely state which was founded in 1733.
							February - The Third Anglo-Maratha War which started in 1817 ends with the Marathas defeated by the British
							1 January - The Peshwa defeated at Koregaon by the British.6 January - Treaty of Mandasor is signed between the British and the Marathas.
							20 February - The Peshwa defeated at Ashti by the British
				</des>
				<color>#D9D9D9</color>
		</data>	
		
		<data>
				<year>1819</year>
				<des>The Ojibwa (Saulteaux) chief also known as William King born Sault Ste Marie 1774, died Red River September 28, 1864 and his children adopted the name Prince.  He defended the Selkirk settlers into Red River, showed them how to subsist in this country and later assisted the survivors after the seven oaks incident.  In gratitude the Selkirk settlers trespassed on his lands and violated the 1817 treaty with Selkirk..  

				</des>
				<color>#4C4C4C</color>
		</data>	
		
		<data>
				<year>1822</year>
				<des>The Ojibwa Shingwahkoonce spoke of the war of 1822, the storming of Mackinaw and the battle of Chippewa.  He spoke of the Ojibwa who lived on the English side of Sault Ste Marie and their forced removal to Manetowahning, on the north shore of Lake Huron.  Francis Broadhead, the snake, attempted to remove the Ojibwa of Sault Ste Marie to a barren island where soil is not good enough to raise potatoes or any other vegetable for their support.  The island they say is composed mostly of large rocks and stones.</des>
				<color>#808080</color>
		</data>	
		
		<data>
				<year>1823</year>
				<des>The Hon. John Adam, Governor-General, 1 Jan.-1 August.
				Lord Amherst, Governor-General, 1823-28.
				The Hon. John Adam, Governor-General, 1 Jan.-1 August.[1]
				Lord Amherst, Governor-General, 1823-28
				The minutes of the Court of Directors constitute the central record of the Company's activities in London. The stockholders' activities are recorded more briefly in the minutes of the Court of Proprietors.</des>
				<color>#1A1A1A</color>
		</data>	
		
		<data>
				<year>1824</year>
				<des>Red Jacket a Seneca was born 1756 Canoga, New York and died January 20, 1830 Buffalo, New York.  He spoke against the missionaries who lived among his people because they do us no good.  If they are not useful to the white people why do they send them to us.  Why do not you keep them home?  These Missionaries know that we do not understand their religion, we cannot read their books, they tell different stories about what it contains, these black coats tell us to raise corn and yet they do not themselves.   </des>
				<color>#0D0D0D</color>
		</data>	
		
		<data>
				<year>1825</year>
				<des>The Prairie du Chien Treaty of this year is alleged to have divided disputed territory between the Dakota Sioux and the Ojibwa.  Chief Shingabawossin of Sault Ste Marie, Wisconsin who signed the Governor Lewis Cass Treaty Du Chin is of the Businause Totem.  Chief Ahmous (little bee) son Waubishgauggauge (white crow) of the Lac Du Flambeau Band is also of the Businause Totem.  Chief Neokautah a Winnebago of Neenah, Wisconsin was a signer of the treaty.</des>
				<color>#1A1A1A</color>
		</data>	
		<data>
				<year>1828</year>
				<des>The Ojibwa of Michilimackinac are divided into two towns based on religion.  The Roman French Catholics separated from their brothers to form a new town encouraged by their priest.  This racist practice is encourage throughout the world by the various religious leaders and is very divisive.F.P. Wrangle reported the Koliuzh no longer attack the Russians out of fear.  This likely assumes the Russians made a major attack on these People.</des>
				<color>#262626</color>
		</data>	
		
		<data>
				<year>1829</year>
				<des>Nancy Shawanahdit, the last of the peace loving Beothuk Race (Red Indians) died at St. John, New Brunswick.  It was noted that she had previously suffered two gun shot wounds from earlier encounters.  The English had used her people as sport hunting targets.   The genocide war against her people by the French and English had ended.  The first Canadians to encountered the migrating Europeans are now extinct. Ralph Emerson said the name of this nation will stink to the world </des>
				<color>#333333</color>
		</data>	
		
		<data>
				<year>1830</year>
				<des>The American Indian removal Act order by President Andrew Jackson, a former Indian fighter, resulted in the relocation of 70,000 Indians from their ancestral lands east of the Mississippi River to the prairies. The Americans considered the plains desolate, fit only for Indians and the Federal Government did its best to put them there. The Indians would be squeezed onto smaller and smaller reservations. So many deaths resulted from the forced removal that it became known as the trail of tears. .  </des>
				<color>#404040</color>
		</data>	
		
		<data>
				<year>1835</year>
				<des>28 January - Medical College, Bengal is established; later became Medical College Kolkata.
				2 February - Madras Medical College is established.Lord Macaulay said the following about India in 1835 in British Parliament.the correct year was 1833 or 1835, but what matters for Indians is the statement itself the first selection a speech on the India bill.From Thomas Babington Macaulay, "Minute of 2 February 1835 </des>
				<color>#4C4C4C</color>
		</data>	
		
		<data>
				<year>1836</year>
				<des>Some suggest the Seminole War (1836-1842) started this year at a cost of twenty million dollars and the death of 1,500 soldiers.  The only effective method used to capture the Seminole was to lure small groups in for parley under the sacred immunity of a flag of truce, then seize them.  They sent 4,000 captured Seminole on the Trail of Tears.  The Americans called off the war as only a few hundred Seminole remained in the swamps.</des>
				<color>#595959</color>
		</data>	
		
		<data>
				<year>1837</year>
				<des>A longboat was sent from Fort Union to Fort McKenzie on the Maris River in upper Missouri River region.  The fort was warned but a quarantine could not be maintained.  The disease spread to 500 lodges of Blackfoot and Piegan (some 5,500 people) at Fort McKenzie.  In this way the disease spread throughout the Missouri River Valley.  The People believed they could run away from the disease and the Assiniboine, Cree, Blood, Blackfoot and Piegan fled north and spread the disease into Canada.  </des>
				<color>#666666</color>
		</data>

		<data>
				<year>1842</year>
				<des>The first Mission at Red Lake by Rev. Frederick Ayres who left Brainerd Spencer in charge. It was abandoned in 1859. The Red Lake Ojibwa raised a significant surplus of grain and vegetables enough to feed fifty families from other bands who wintered 1842-43 at Red Lake to escape starvation in their home areas. In the summer they join the Red River Metis in their bison buffalo hunts.Walton, George H. Fearless and Free: the Seminole Indian War,1835-1842. Indianapolis, </des>
				<color>#737373</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1843</year>
				<des>There was still a surplus of grain available at Red Lake as $100.00 worth was purchased by Alfred Brunson, Sub-Agent at La Pointe, Wisconsin for distribution to the Ojibwa of other areas.William Sublette, fur trader, led a party of pleasure hunters out into the plains from St. Louis. Among the party was the Scottish nobleman Captain Sir William Drummond Stewart and William Clark Kennerly with eighty men. They left the prairie strewan for miles with the bodies of dead bison (buffalo).</des>
				<color>#808080</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1844</year>
				<des>Bishop George Mountain reported from Red River that native cult objects represent tangible proof of imposture, delusion and darkness.  Father LeJeunne believed the wicked liberty of the savages needs the yoke of god to prevent them from following their inclination.Ojaouanon a Chief of Walpole Island debated with Jesuit Superior Pierre Chazelle.  The Great Spirit sees and knows everything, taught the elders who teach the people and we keep it in our hearts and will never renounce our faith.</des>
				<color>#8C8C8C</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1845</year>
				<des>1st Sikh War, 1845-46.
				Grant Medical College opened in Bombay.The Sikh kingdom of Punjab was expanded and consolidated by Maharajah Ranjit Singh during the early years of the nineteenth century, about the same time as the British-controlled territories were advanced by conquest or annexation to the borders of the Punjab.He hired American and European mercenary soldiers to train his artillery.</des>
				<color>#999999</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1846</year>
				<des>At Sault Ste Marie on the American side lives seven to eight hundred People whereas on the Canadian side there are only a few Metis and many Ojibwa.  A census by J.P. Hays, a sub agent from La Pointe Wisconsin placed the Red Lake clan as 1,200 being located at Pembina, Red Lake and Winnipeg Lakes.  He said their main substance is agriculture producing 2,000 bushels corn.  No mention is made of the other crops.  In winter they hunt bison buffalo west of the Red River. </des>
				<color>#A6A6A6</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1848</year>
				<des>2nd Sikh War, 1848-49.Annexation of Sattara.2nd Sikh War, 1848-49.The California Gold Rush (1848–1855) began on January 24, 1848, when gold was found by James W. Marshall at Sutter's Mill in Coloma, California.[1] The first to hear confirmed information of the Gold Rush were the people in Oregon, the Sandwich Islands (Hawaii), and Latin America.Gold mining also caused environmental harm to rivers and lakes.</des>
				<color>#B2B2B2</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1849</year>
				<des>2nd Sikh War, 1848-49.
				Annexation of Punjab.
				Annexation of Jaitpur and Sambalpur.
				Find 4 collections in India from 1840-1849 at WorldVitalRecords.com.Please select one of the decades below to get access to all the family history resources we have for India for a given time period.But by 1849, during the gold rush, the non-Indian population of California had grown to 100,000.</des>
				<color>#BFBFBF</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1850</year>
				<des>The ceremony of turning the first sod for the Great Indian Peninsula Railway from Mumbai to Kalyan was performed by J. P. Willoughby at a place near Sion.The Michigan Constitution read :Neither slavery nor involuntary servitude, unless for the punishment of crime, shall be tolerated in this state."  Some believe they didn't realize this constitution legalized slavery until 1963 when it was finally revoked.</des>
				<color>#CCCCCC</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1852</year>
				<des>Katimin a village of the Karok People on the banks of the Klamath River about a mile from the mouth of the Salmon River in California is burned by the white people.  The Karok believed this location was the center of the earth and was a very sacred area.  It was the scene of many yearly ceremonies.It offers students the opportunity to study the history of 19th-century India and its imperial contexts in greater depth.</des>
				<color>#D9D9D9</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1853</year>
				<des>April 16 - The first Indian train popularly called Aag Gadi which steamed off from Bombay to Thane. The train was drawn by three engines and covered the 34km distance in 57 minutes.There are no prerequisites for this module, but as a History ‘special subject’ it is designed to build upon work students have done in their first and second years, especially in relation to the history of imperialism and South Asia including the core course "Making of the Modern World"</des>
				<color>#737373</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1856</year>
				<des>25 July - Hindu Widows' Remarriage Act, 1856
				Annexation of the Kingdom of Oudh
				The Indian Rebellion of 1857 began as a mutiny of sepoys of the East India Company's army on 10 May 1857, in the town of Meerut, and soon escalated into other mutinies and civilian rebellions largely in the upper Gangetic plain and central India, with the major hostilities confined to present-day Uttar Pradesh, Bihar, northern Madhya Pradesh, and the Delhi region</des>
				<color>#999999</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1857</year>
				<des>10 May (starting date of the revolt)- Indian rebellion of 1857 (also known as the Sepoy Mutiny) or The First War Of Indian Independence, widespread uprising in northern and central India against the rule of the British East India Company.the Revolt of 1857, the Uprising of 1857, the Sepoy Rebellion and the Sepoy Mutiny. The Mutiny was a result of various grievances. However the flashpoint was reached when the soldiers were asked to bite off the paper cartridges for their rifles which they believed.</des>
				<color>#B2B2B2</color>
		</data>		
		
	
		<data>
				<year>1858</year>
				<des>February - General Rose relieves Saugor; Campbell's Army of Oudh assembles on the Kanpur-Lucknow road to await Jang Bahadur's Gurkha army
				March - Lucknow is recaptured on 21 March; Central India campaign continuesIndian Rebellion of 1857 urged British Government to pass this Act. To calm down the after effects of 1857 revolt, the Act of 1858 was introduced.The Company's territories in India were to be vested in the Queen</des>
				<color>#0D0D0D</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1859</year>
				<des>The Indian rebellion of 1857 ends (formally declared in July).Execution of Tatya Tope (Ramachandra Pandurang Tope), 18 April 1859, a Maratha leader in the Indian Rebellion of 1857.January - General Sir Hugh Rose begins the Central India campaign Sir Colin Campbell begins the campaign to recapture Lucknow; trial of Bahadur Shah, King of Delhi, from 27 January
				 the Company ceasing to exercise its power</des>
				<color>#1A1A1A</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1860</year>
				<des>Later, on the annual bison (buffalo) hunt, the White Horse Plains Metis visited the Dakota Sioux village of 1,500 warriors to make peace.  The Dakota Sioux had sent a peace party to the Metis camp requesting a conference.  Following peace, the Dakota Sioux performed the bison (buffalo) Head Dance.  In the evening the young single girls, in white deer skin, profusely ornamented with porcupine quills and beads, danced and sung much to the enjoyment of the young Metis hunters, who made many presents.</des>
				<color>#262626</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1861</year>
				<des>Boys' High School and College, Allahabad, is founded.In the evening the young single girls, in white deer skin, profusely ornamented with porcupine quills and beads
				The Delhi Department of Police is founded. Rabindranath Tagore, poet, artist, playwright, novelist and composer24 September: Bhikaiji Cama, independence campaigner (died 1936).Date unknown: Devaki Nandan Khatri, first author of mystery novels in Hindi (died 1913)</des>
				<color>#333333</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1862</year>
				<des>Senator Ramsey of Minnesota met with 2,000 Red Lake Ojibwa to conclude the 1862 treaty that is deferred due to the Sibley War.  The settlement would cost ten million dollars.  Alexander Ramsey also entered into treaty with the Chippewa (Ojibwa) of Pembina and Turtle Mountain who are descendents of Red Lake.  They previously descended from the Lake Superior Ojibwa.  No distinction is made between Indian and Metis at this time.fter two years of killing and plundering on July 28 at Killdeer Mountain</des>
				<color>#4C4C4C</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1863</year>
				<des>Senator Ramsey of Minnesota met with 2,000 Red Lake Ojibwa to conclude the 1862 treaty that is deferred due to the Sibley War.  The settlement would cost ten million dollars.  Alexander Ramsey also entered into treaty with the Chippewa (Ojibwa) of Pembina and Turtle Mountain who are descendents of Red Lake.  They previously descended from the Lake Superior Ojibwa.  No distinction is made between Indian and Metis at this time.</des>
				<color>#4C4C4C</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1864</year>
				<des>After two years of killing and plundering on July 28 at Killdeer Mountain that is South East of Watford, North Dakota the 2,200 man army led by Sully attacked a Dakota village massacring 100 to 150 people.  The prospectors and miners in Shasta and Tehama Counties in California slaughtered 2,950 Yana People men, women and children within a few days with only 50 escaping bringing these people to extinction as a tribe.</des>
				<color>#595959</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1866</year>
				<des>History of Norwich, Connecticut: From Its Possession by the Indians, to the Year 1866
				17 August - Mahbub Ali Khan was born, Asaf Jah VI, sixth Nizam of Hyderabad (died 1911).The History has been entirely re-written, and is, in fact, a new work. The author has considered it an imperative duty to review all the sources of information, and to make it as complete a town history as the materials would permit.Annual report of the commissioner of Indian affairs, for the year 1878.</des>
				<color>#666666</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1868</year>
				<des>Bank of Bombay established.Earthquake in Ahmedabad, Bombay State.
				The Indian Councils Act 1861 was an Act of the Parliament of the United Kingdom that transformed the Viceroy of India's executive council into a cabinet run on the portfolio system.The Governor General was given the power to create new provinces for legislative purposes
				The History of Norwich, published in 1845, having been for several years out of print, it seems desirable that the public should be furnished with a new and more complete work</des>
				<color>#737373</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1869</year>
				<des>Sir John Lawrence, Viceroy
				Richard Bourke, 6th Earl of Mayo, Viceroy 
				La Martinière Girls School is founded in Lucknow.
				11 April - Kasturba Gandhi, wife of Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi .
				2 October  Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi, political and spiritual leader in India and the Indian independence movement  ,assassinated .</des>
				<color>#808080</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1870</year>
				<des>The first submarine telegraph cable from UK landed in Bombay.
				The United Service Institution (USI) was founded.
				January 3 – Construction of the Brooklyn Bridge begins.
				January 6 – The Musikverein, Vienna is inaugurated in Austria-Hungary.
				January 10 – John D. Rockefeller incorporates Standard Oil.
				January 15 – A political cartoon for the first time symbolizes the United States Democratic Party with a donkey ("A Live Jackass Kicking a Dead Lion" by Thomas Nast for Harper's Weekly).</des>
				<color>#8C8C8C</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1871</year>
				<des>October 12-Criminal Tribes Act (CTA) enacted by British rule in India, which named over 160 communities "Criminal Tribes", i.e. hereditary criminals. It was repealed in 1949, after Independence of India.October 12 – Criminal Tribes Act (CTA) enacted by British rule in India, which named over 160 communities "Criminal Tribes", i.e. hereditary criminals. It was repealed in 1949, after Independence of India</des>
				<color>#999999</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1872</year>
				<des>BIRTHS

				14 April - Abdullah Yusuf Ali, Islamic scholar who translated the Qur'an into English (died 1953).
	A political cartoon for the first time symbolizes the United States Democratic Party with a donkey ("A Live Jackass Kicking a Dead Lion"			15 August - Sri Aurobindo, nationalist, scholar, poet, mystic, evolutionary philosopher, yogi and guru (died 1950).
				 Partnership contained in the Indian Contract Act were repealed respectively in the year 1930 and 1932 </des>
				<color>#A6A6A6</color>

				</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1873</year>
				<des>Incumbents

				Thomas Baring, 1st Earl of Northbrook, Viceroy
				Events

				Bihar famine of 1873–74
				Births

					19 December - Upendranath Brahmachari, scientist and medical practitionerJan 1st - Origin of Japanese Era
Jan 6th - Pope Pius IX encyclical "On the Church in Armenia"
Jan 6th - US Congress begins investigating Crédit Mobilier scandal
Jan 11th - 1st livestock market newspaper published, Drover's Journal, Chicago</des>
				<color>#B2B2B2</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1874</year>
				<des>Bihar famine of 1873-74
				The Prince of Wales visits British India.
				January - The Pangkor Treaty (also known as the Pangkor Engagement), by which the British extended their control over, first the Sultanate of Perak and later the other independent Malay States, is signed.
January 1 - New York City annexes The Bronx.
</des>
				<color>#BFBFBF</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1875</year>
				<des>Muhammedan Anglo-Oriental College, founded by Sir Syed Ahmed Khan in Aligarh (now Uttar Pradesh); later became Aligarh Muslim University in 1920.Though the surrender of Delhi to British forces, in less than a year after the rebels had first captured it, and the containment of the rebellion in the Punjab pointed to the reassertion of British authority
				8 November - The Prince of Wales (afterwards King Edward VII) visits Bombay.</des>
				<color>#CCCCCC</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1876</year>
				<des>Incumbents

				Thomas Baring, 1st Earl of Northbrook, Viceroy
				Robert Bulwer-Lytton, 1st Earl of Lytton, Viceroy 
				Events

				1 May — Queen Victoria is proclaimed Empress of India.
				Births

				15 September — Sharat Chandra Chatterji, novelist .
				25 December — Muhammad Ali Jinnah, Statesman and founder of Pakistan </des>
				<color>#D9D9D9</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1877</year>
				<des>Celebrations in darbars are held in India now that Queen Victoria is Empress of India.it was not until 1859-60 that the last pockets of resistance to British rule were destroyed. In the meantime, the East India Company had been dissolved, and the administration of India passed directly into the hands of the Crown.1 May — Queen Victoria is proclaimed Empress of India.In the meantime, the East India Company had been dissolved, and the administration of India passed directly into the hands of the Crown.
				Births</des>
				<color>#E6E6E6</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1878</year>
				<des>Incumbents
			Empress of India — Queen Victoria
			Viceroy of India - Robert Bulwer-Lytton, 1st Earl of LyttonThe English had used her people as sport hunting targets.   The genocide war against her people by the French and English had ended.</des>
				<color>#0D0D0D</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1879</year>
				<des>Incumbents

				Empress of India — Queen Victoria
				Viceroy of India - Robert Bulwer-Lytton, 1st Earl of Lytton
				Events

				The Bombay Dyeing and Mfg. Co. Ltd., a textile company, established
				Births

				K. N. Sivaraja Pillai (1879-1941) Indian historian, dravidologist and professor .</des>
				<color>#808080</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1880</year>
				<des>16 March — Rajshekhar Basu was born, writer, chemist and lexicographer (died 1960).
				31 July — Munshi Premchand was born, foremost Writer in Hindu-Urdu Literature and Indian Freedom fighter (died 8 October 1936).The Ojibwa of Michilimackinac are divided into two towns based on religion.  The Roman French Catholics separated from their brothers to form a new town encouraged by their priest</des>
				<color>#0D0D0D</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1881</year>
				<des>Incumbents

			Empress of India — Queen Victoria
			Viceroy of India - George Robinson, 1st Marquess of Ripon

			The Roman French Catholics separated from their brothers to form a new town encouraged by their priest
			Births

			November — Darwan Singh Negi, recipient of the Victoria Cross for gallantry in 1914 .</des>
				<color>#1A1A1A</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1882</year>
				<des>1 July — Bidhan Chandra Roy was born, second Chief Minister of West Bengal (d.1962).
				11 December — Subramanya Bharathi was born, poet, independence fighter and reformer (d.1921). The first Canadians to encountered the migrating Europeans are now extinct. Ralph Emerson said the name of this nation will stink to the world</des>
				<color>#262626</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1883</year>
				<des>15 September - Bombay Natural History Society founded.
				Calcutta International Festival beginsThe American Indian removal Act order by President Andrew Jackson, a former Indian fighter, resulted in the relocation of 70,000 Indians from their ancestral lands east of the Mississippi River to the prairies.There was still a surplus of grain available at Red Lake as $100.00 worth was purchased by Alfred Brunson, Sub-Agent at La Pointe, Wisconsin for distribution to the Ojibwa</des>
				<color>#333333</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1884</year>
				<des>DEATHS
				12 December — Charles Phillip Brown, writer and colonial official.Bishop George Mountain reported from Red River that native cult objects represent tangible proof of imposture, delusion and darkness.  Father LeJeunne believed the wicked liberty of the savages needs the yoke of god to prevent them from following their inclination.Ojaouanon a Chief of Walpole Island debated with Jesuit Superior Pierre Chazelle.</des>
				<color>#404040</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1885</year>
				<des>First President of Indian National Congress — W. C. Banerjee; First Secretary of Indian National Congress — A. O. Hume; Dadabbhai Naoroji gave the name Indian National Congress.The American Indian removal Act order by President Andrew Jackson, a former Indian fighter, resulted in the relocation of 70,000 Indians from their ancestral lands east of the Mississippi River to the prairies.the forced removal that it became known as the trail of tears</des>
				<color>#4C4C4C</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1886</year>
				<des>Incumbents

				Empress of India — Queen Victoria
				Viceroy of India - The Earl of Dufferin

				Births[edit]
				16 January — Chenganoor Raman Pillai, Kathakali artiste (d.1980)
				The first Mission at Red Lake by Rev. Frederick Ayres who left Brainerd Spencer in charge. It was abandoned in 1859. The Red Lake Ojibwa raised a significant surplus of grain and vegetables enough to feed fifty families </des>
				<color>#595959</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1887</year>
				<des>Incumbents

				Empress of India — Queen Victoria
				Viceroy of India - The Earl of Dufferin
				Events

				Trinity College London examiners conducted music examinations in Mumbai for the first time.
				Births

				22 December — Srinivasa Ramanujan, mathematician. Medical College, Bengal is established; later became Medical College Kolkata.
				2 February - Madras Medical College is established.Lord Macaulay said the following about India in 1835 in British Parliament.</des>
				<color>#666666</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1888</year>
				<des>Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi left to study in London.Some suggest the Seminole War (1836-1842) started this year at a cost of twenty million dollars and the death of 1,500 soldiers.  The only effective method used to capture the Seminole was to lure small groups in for parley under the sacred immunity of a flag of truce, then seize them.  They sent 4,000 captured Seminole on the Trail of Tears. </des>
				<color>#737373</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1889</year>
				<des>2 February — Rajkumari Amrit Kaur was born, freedom fighter, social activist and Health Minister (d.1964).
				14 November — Jawaharlal Nehru born, politician and 1st Prime Minister of India (d.1964).
				22 December — Srinivasa Ramanujan, mathematician. Medical College, Bengal is established; later became Medical College Kolkata.
				2 February - Madras Medical College is established.Lord Macaulay </des>
				<color>#808080</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1890</year>
				<des>A. R. Krishnashastry was born, writer, researcher and translator (died 1968)A longboat was sent from Fort Union to Fort McKenzie on the Maris River in upper Missouri River region.  The fort was warned but a quarantine could not be maintained.  The disease spread to 500 lodges of Blackfoot and Piegan .A longboat was sent from Fort Union to Fort McKenzie on the Maris River in upper Missouri River region.</des>
				<color>#8C8C8C</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1891</year>
				<des>Incumbents

				Empress of India — Queen Victoria
				Viceroy of India - Henry Petty-Fitzmaurice, 5th Marquess of Lansdowne
				There was still a surplus of grain available at Red Lake as $100.00 worth was purchased by Alfred Brunson, Sub-Agent at La Pointe, Wisconsin for distribution to the Ojibwa of other areas.William Sublette</des>
				<color>#999999</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1892</year>
				<des>4 January — J. C. Kumarappa was born, economist (d.1960).ishop George Mountain reported from Red River that native cult objects represent tangible proof of imposture, delusion and darkness.  Father LeJeunne believed the wicked liberty of the savages needs the yoke of god to prevent.surplus of grain and vegetables enough to feed fifty families from other bands who wintered </des>
				<color>#A6A6A6</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1893</year>
				<des>Incumbents

				Empress of India — Queen Victoria
				Viceroy of India - Henry Petty-Fitzmaurice, 5th Marquess of Lansdowne.disease spread throughout the Missouri River Valley.  The People believed they could run away from the disease and the Assiniboine, Cree, Blood, Blackfoot and Piegan fled north and spread the disease into Canada</des>
				<color>#B2B2B2</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1894</year>
				<des>Births

				1 January — Satyendra Nath Bose, physicist (d.1974).
				21 February — Shanti Swaroop Bhatnagar, scientist (d.1955).
				25 February — Meher Baba, mystic and spiritual master (d.1969).Red Jacket a Seneca was born 1756 Canoga, New York and died January 20, 1830 Buffalo, New York.  He spoke against the missionaries who lived among his people because they do us no good.</des>
				<color>#BFBFBF</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1895</year>
				<des>Incumbents
 Waubishgauggauge (white crow) of the Lac Du Flambeau Band is also of the Businause Totem.  Chief Neokautah a Winnebago of Neenah, Wisconsin was a signer of the treaty.
				Empress of India — Queen Victoria
				Viceroy of India - Victor Bruce, 9th Earl of Elgin.Red Jacket a Seneca was born 1756 Canoga, New York and died January 20, 1830 Buffalo, New York.  He spoke against the missionaries who lived among his people because they do us no good.</des>
				<color>#CCCCCC</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1896</year>
				<des>In Bombay plague epidemic bubonic plague killed thousands
				A famine started in Bundelkhand and continued into 1897
				The Malabar Marriage Act, 1896 was passed. Waubishgauggauge (white crow) of the Lac Du Flambeau Band is also of the Businause Totem.  Chief Neokautah a Winnebago of Neenah, Wisconsin was a signer of the treaty.</des>
				<color>#D9D9D9</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1897</year>
				<des>The Indian famine of 1896–97 comes to a close
				Scindia School is established in Gwalior
				Frontier War of 1897-98. Waubishgauggauge (white crow) of the Lac Du Flambeau Band is also of the Businause Totem.  Chief Neokautah a Winnebago of Neenah, Wisconsin was a signer of the treaty.</des>
				<color>#999999</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1898</year>
				<des>Incumbents

				Empress of India — Queen Victoria
				Viceroy of India - Victor Bruce, 9th Earl of Elgin
				Events

				Frontier War of 1897-98
				Births

				19 January — Vishnu Sakharam Khandekar, writer .
				25 November — Debaki Bose, film director, writer and actor .
				2 December — Indra Lal Roy, World War I flying ace, killed in action .</des>
				<color>#F2F2F2</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
				<year>1899</year>
				<des>Incumbents

				Empress of India — Queen Victoria
				Viceroy of India - Victor Bruce, 9th Earl of Elgin
				Viceroy of India - George Curzon, 1st Marquess Curzon of Kedleston (from 6 January)</des>
				<color>#0D0D0D</color>
		</data>		
		
		<data>
<year>1901</year>
<des>Incumbents

Empress of India — Queen Victoria until 22 January
Emperor of India — Edward VII from 22 January
Viceroy of India - George Curzon, 1st Marquess Curzon of Kedleston
Events

The first reliable census in India is taken.
Births

2 July — Kalindi Charan Panigrahi, poet, novelist, story writer, dramatist and essayist (died 1991).
3 Nov - Prithviraj Kapoor, actor, producer</des>
<color>#1A1A1A</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1902</year>
<des>Incumbents

Emperor of India – Edward VII
Viceroy of India - George Curzon, 1st Marquess Curzon of Kedleston
Events

United Provinces of Agra and Oudh is established 
Births

10 October - K. Shivaram Karanth, writer, social activist, environmentalist, Yakshagana artist, movie maker and thinker .</des>
<color>#262626</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1903</year>
<des>Incumbents

Emperor of India – Edward VII
Viceroy of India - George Curzon, 1st Marquess Curzon of Kedleston
Events

1 January - Edward VII of the United Kingdom is proclaimed Emperor of India.
Births

3 April - Kamaladevi Chattopadhyay, social reformer and freedom fighter.
Gopi Krishna, yogi, mystic, teacher, social reformer and writer .
</des>
<color>#333333</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1904</year>
<des>March 18, the Ancient Monuments Preservation Act is passed
the gun carriage factory is established in Jabalpur
October 31 - The Kumbakonam Bank Limited, is incorporated as a limited company (later known as the City Union Bank)
the secret Abhinav Bharat Society is founded by Vinayak Damodar Savarkar</des>
<color>#404040</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1905</year>
<des>4 April - The 1905 Kangra earthquake kills 20,000.
Partition of Bengal.
George, Prince of Wales and Princess Mary tour India, 1905-06</des>
<color>#4C4C4C</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1906</year>
<des>George, Prince of Wales, and Princess Mary tour India, 1905-06[1]
1 January - British India officially adopts Indian Standard Time.
11 September - Mahatma Gandhi coins the term Satyagraha to characterize the Non-Violence movement in South Africa.</des>
<color>#595959</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1907</year>
<des>5 June - Bochasanwasi Shri Akshar Purushottam Swaminarayan Sanstha, a sect of Hinduism, is established by Swami Yagnapurushdas.
26 December - Surat Split of Congress- Split into Moderates and Radicals- </des>
<color>#666666</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1908</year>
<des>March 17 - the Tinnevely riot breaks out in Tirunelveli
May - the trial of the Alipore bomb case commences (and continues until 1909)
September 28 - the Great Musi flood kills 15000 people</des>
<color>#737373</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1909</year>
<des>Incumbents

Emperor of India – Edward VII
Viceroy of India - Gilbert Elliot-Murray-Kynynmound, 4th Earl of Minto
Events

Adoption of schemes of reform
Births

3 January - M. K. Thyagaraja Bhagavathar, actor and Carnatic singer .
10 February - Pisharoth Rama Pisharoty, physicist and meteorologist </des>
<color>#808080</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1910</year>
<des>Incumbents

Emperor of India – Edward VII until May 6, George V
Viceroy of India - Gilbert Elliot-Murray-Kynynmound, 4th Earl of Minto
Viceroy of India - Charles Hardinge, 1st Baron Hardinge of Penshurst 
Events

4 April - Sri Aurobindo began his spiritual pursuits in Puducherry.
Births

30 January - Chidambaram Subramaniam, politician and Minister 
19 May - Nathuram Godse, assassin of Mahatma Gandhi, executed .</des>
<color>#8C8C8C</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1911</year>
<des>18 February - Henry Piquet, flying a Humber biplane, carried mail from Allahabad to Naini junction which was the first flight in India.</des>
<color>#999999</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1912</year>
<des>On February 14, 1912 His Majesty the King George V gave a speech in the British Parliament about his visit to the imperial colonies and expressed his trust to India people and government he saw during his visit to India in 1911.</des>
<color>#A6A6A6</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1913</year>
<des>3 May- Raja Harischandra, First full length movie of India released. Beginning of Indian Film Industry.
Rabindranath Tagore (1861–1941), Bengali poet, got the Nobel Prize in Literature for his book of lyrics called Gitanjali translated into English by himself.</des>
<color>#B2B2B2</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1914</year>
<des>In August India as the British colony sends troops to Europe to participate as the British fighting partner in World War I against Germany. This force was a part of the British Expeditionary Force sent to Belgium.</des>
<color>#BFBFBF</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1915</year>
<des>Calcutta School of Music is established by Phillpe Sandre.</des>
<color>#CCCCCC</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1916</year>
<des>The Hindus leading the Indian National Congress Party hammer out an alliance - the Lucknow Pact - with India's Muslim League.</des>
<color>#D9D9D9</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1917</year>
<des>The Indian National Congress demands self-government for India.[1]
20 August - The secretary of state for India makes the announcement that British policy in India calls for the gradual development of self-governing institutions and the progressive realization of responsible government.</des>
<color>#E6E6E6</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1918</year>
<des>Incumbents

Emperor of India – George V
Viceroy of India - Frederic Thesiger, 1st Viscount Chelmsford
Events

End of first world war.
Births

January 12- Maharishi Mahesh Yogi
24 August - Sikander Bakht, politician.</des>
<color>#F2F2F2</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1919</year>
<des>April - Disturbances in Delhi and Punjab and martial law in Punjab;.[1]
11 April - Serious riots in Ahmedabad.[2]
13 April - At the Jallianwala Bagh Massacre in Amritsar, Punjab, British and Gurkha troops massacre 379 Sikhs.</des>
<color>#666666</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1920</year>
<des>Muhammedan Anglo-Oriental College, founded by Sir Syed Ahmed Khan in Aligarh in 1875, becomes Aligarh Muslim University.
8 July - The House of Commons adopts the findings of the Hunter report.[1]
Founding of the University of Lucknow</des>
<color>#0D0D0D</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1921</year>
<des>8 April - Permanent Advisory Council of Princes inaugurated; Council of State and Legislative Assembly inaugurated.[1]
23 December – Visva-Bharati University is inaugurated.</des>
<color>#1A1A1A</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1922</year>
<des>February - The Chauri Chaura incident occurs, where a mob of about 3000 kills some policemen. With the Non-cooperation movement (NCM) taking an increasingly violent form, this is the last straw to Gandhi's sense of discipline.</des>
<color>#262626</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1923</year>
<des>Incumbents

Emperor of India – George V
Viceroy of India - The Earl of Reading
Events

The Madras Province Swarajya Party was established under the leadership of S. Sathyamurthy and S. Srinivasa Iyengar.
Births

10 March - Ranjit Lal Jetley, soldier and scientist.
21 March - Nirmala Srivastava, founder of Sahaja Yoga</des>
<color>#333333</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1924</year>
<des>12 January - Gopinath Saha shoots a man he erroneously thinks is a Police commissioner of Calcutta, Charles Augustus Tegart - he is arrested soon after.
February - Mohandas Gandhi is released prematurely on medical grounds.</des>
<color>#404040</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1925</year>
<des>3 February - The first ever electric train of India completes its journey from Victoria Terminus to Kurla on the Central Line (Mumbai Suburban Railway).[1]
9 March - 1 May Pink's War; RAF operations against tribesmen in Waziristan</des>
<color>#4C4C4C</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1926</year>
<des>April - Hindu-Muslim strife in Calcutta.[1]
15 July - BEST buses make its début in Bombay.
24 November - Sri Aurobindo retires, leaving the Mother to run the Sri Aurobindo Ashram in Pondicherry</des>
<color>#595959</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1927</year>
<des>18 January - Council House in New Delhi is opened.[1]
28 September - Fatal communal riots in Dehra Dun, U.P.[2]
12 November - Mahatma Gandhi made his first and last visit to Ceylon.</des>
<color>#666666</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1928</year>
<des>February - the Simon Commission lands in India[1]
May - India wins Hockey Gold Medal at the Amsterdam Olympics - Games of the IXth Olympiad.
December - Board of Control for Cricket in India is formed.</des>
<color>#737373</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1929</year>
<des>6 January - Mother Teresa arrives Kolkata to work amongst India's poorest and diseased people
29 December - All India Congress in Lahore demands Indian independence.
The radical nationalists, led by Jawaharlal Nehru.</des>
<color>#808080</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1930</year>
<des>25 January - Mohandas Gandhi released again.
10 February - New Delhi becomes the capital of India.
27 February - Chandrasekhar Azad martyrdom in an encounter with the British in Allahabad.
</des>
<color>#8C8C8C</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1931</year>
<des>Third civil disobedience campaign.[1]
3 January - British arrest and intern Mohandas Gandhi and Vallabhbhai Patel.
February - Terrorism in Bengal</des>
<color>#999999</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1932</year>
<des>Third civil disobedience campaign.[1]
3 January - British arrest and intern Mohandas Gandhi and Vallabhbhai Patel.
February - Terrorism in Bengal.</des>
<color>#A6A6A6</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1933</year>
<des>January - Extensive prosecutions of Communists for treason.[1]
Indian National Congress meeting at Calcutta prevented by the police.[2]
1 May - Gandhi released</des>
<color>#B2B2B2</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1934</year>
<des>15 January - There is an 8.4 earthquake in India and Nepal in which more than 10,000 people die.
7 April - Mahatma Gandhi suspended his campaign of civil disobedience.</des>
<color>#BFBFBF</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1935</year>
<des>Earthquake destroyed Quetta.
2 August - Government of India Bill, 1935, became law; it provided for development of a popular constitution</des>
<color>#CCCCCC</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1936</year>
<des>3 March - Legislative Assembly passed a motion to terminate the Ottawa trade agreement.
8 June - All India Radio was founded.
15-18 October - Religious riots in Bombay.</des>
<color>#D9D9D9</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1937</year>
<des>Provincial autonomy begins with Congress winning power in many states.
20 February - Completion of election to legislative assemblies.[1]
1 April - Provincial autonomy began; Burma and Aden are separated from India</des>
<color>#E6E6E6</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1938</year>
<des>Minor engagements on the North West Frontier throughout the year.
December - Announcement that the Ottawa trade agreeement would not be continued after 31 March 1939.</des>
<color>#808080</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1939</year>
<des>World War II breaks out in 1939 and political dead lock in India.The ensuring years were, in a manner of speaking, to be devoted to reconstruction; and the memory of the harsh measures adopted by the British to repress the disturbances had instilled some quiet in the countryside. However, agrarian unrest has a rather long history, and there is always just cause for Indian peasants, laboring under difficult conditions</des>
<color>#404040</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1940</year>
<des>The Muslim League demanded a separate homeland for the Indian Muslims openly for the first time at its annual session held in Lahore.
19 November - The Central Legislative Assembly rejects the Finance Bill.
</des>
<color>#0D0D0D</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1941</year>
<des>Incumbents

Emperor of India – George VI
Viceroy of India - Victor Hope, 2nd Marquess of Linlithgow
Events

28 January - A customs union is established with French India.
Births

1 January - Govardhan Asrani, actor.
10 April - Mani Shankar Aiyar, politician and Minister.
5 July - Nitin Desai, Under Secretary General, United Nations, 1993–2003</des>
<color>#1A1A1A</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1942</year>
<des>March - Freedom fighter Jawaharlal Nehru's daughter Indira marries a Parsi lawyer and freedom fighter, Feroze Gandhi against her father's wishes.
The Cripps mission's proposals are rejected by Congress</des>
<color>#262626</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1943</year>
<des>Bengal famine of 1943
10 February - 3 March - Mohandas Gandhi maintains a hunger strike to protest his imprisonment.
5 December - The Japanese attack the Port of Kolkata</des>
<color>#333333</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1944</year>
<des>March to June - Operation U-Go; Japanese defeated in Manipur.[1]
8 March - Battle of Imphal begins
20 March – Battle of Sangshak begins</des>
<color>#404040</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1945</year>
<des>8 August - Subhas Chandra Bose, one of Indian Freedom movement leaders, allegedly dies in a plane crash in Taiwan.
20 September - Mohandas Gandhi and Jawaharlal Nehru demand that British troops leave India.</des>
<color>#4C4C4C</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1946</year>
<des>January - Royal Air Force Mutiny of 1946 of British and Indian air force units
11 February - I.N.A. trial demonstrations in Calcutta, several killed
12 February - Hartal in Calcutta over the killing of demonstrators the previous day</des>
<color>#595959</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1947</year>
<des>15 March - Hindus and Muslims clash in Punjab.
17 May - Tripura is officially ceded to India after 200 years of independent rule.
7 August - The Bombay Municipal Corporation formally takes over the Bombay Electric Supply and Transport (BEST).</des>
<color>#666666</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1948</year>
<des>30 January - Assassination of Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi The spiritual leader of India Mahatma Gandhi is assassinated by Nathuram Godse.
15 February - Junagadh and Manavadar (princely state) Rescinds accession to Pakistan, accedes to India.</des>
<color>#737373</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1949</year>
<des>1 January - After eight months of fighting between the Indian forces and the Pakistan Army agreed to a ceasefire, ordered by the United Nations Security Council, takes effect in Kashmir region.
1 April - The Reserve Bank of India is established.</des>
<color>#808080</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1950</year>
<des>25 January – Election Commission is established.
26 January – The Constitution comes into force making India a republic, the day is observed as Republic Day ever since and declares Kashmir and Jammu into the Indian state of Jammu and Kashmir, </des>
<color>#8C8C8C</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1951</year>
<des>18 June – First Amendment of the Constitution of India says "state can make special provisions for advancement of any backward class"
5 November – Central Railway is formed by the merger of several government-owned railways.
</des>
<color>#999999</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1952</year>
<des>17 April – Membership of the first lok sabha starts.
13 May – Jawaharlal Nehru forms his first government.
15 May – G.V. Mavlankar handles the charge as Lok Sabha Speaker.</des>
<color>#A6A6A6</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1953
</year>
<des>15 June – Indian Airlines created.
Air India nationalised.
Government of India sets up first backward classes commission headed by Kaka Kalelkar.</des>
<color>#B2B2B2</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1954
</year>
<des>22 March – Jayendra Saraswathi becomes the 70th Shankaracharya of Kanchi.
5 July – The Andhra Pradesh High Court is established.
6 November – Bombay Electricity Board is formed.</des>
<color>#BFBFBF</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1955</year>
<des>The Imperial Bank of India, the oldest (est. 1921) and the largest commercial bank of the Indian subcontinent, was transformed into the State Bank of India.
The Hindu Marriage Act enacted</des>
<color>#CCCCCC</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1956</year>
<des>8 March- M. Ananthasayanam Ayyangar handles the charge as Lok Sabha Speaker.
20 March- Sardar Hukam Singh handles the charge as Lok Sabha Deputy Speaker.
14 October – Dr. B. R. Ambedkar, Indian Untouchable leader, converts to Buddhism along with 385,000 followers. See Neo-Buddhism.</des>
<color>#D9D9D9</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1957</year>
<des>India passes a bill making Kashmir under its control as part of the Union.
5 April – First elected government of Kerala. Communist Party of India won the elections and E. M. S. Namboodiripad became the first chief minister of united Kerala.</des>
<color>#E6E6E6</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1958</year>
<des>18 to 20 May – 16th Session of Indian Labour Congress held at New Delhi
11 September – The Armed Forces (Special Powers) Act is passed by the Parliament.</des>
<color>#333333</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1959</year>
<des>17 March – Tenzin Gyatso, the 14th Dalai Lama, flees Tibet and travels to India.
September – Doordarshan-India's national state-owned broadcaster established.
Bajaj Auto obtains license from Government of India to manufacture two- and three-wheelers in India.</des>
<color>#404040</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1960</year>
<des>1 May - Gujarat State and Maharashtra State are formed from the State of Bombay as laid down by the States Reorganisation Act.owing to disturbances over large parts of Western India, a committee was appointed by the Government of Bombay to report on the “riots in Poona and Ahmednagar.”</des>
<color>#0D0D0D</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1961</year>
<des>1 November - The Hungry generation Movement is launched in Calcutta.
17 December - India occupies Goa. On May 12th of that year, in the village of Supa in Bhimthari taluka of Poona, there was an outbreak of violence</des>
<color>#1A1A1A</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1962</year>
<des>3 April - Jawaharlal Nehru is elected de facto Prime Minister of India.
6 May - India defeats the Philippines in the Eastern Zone final of 1962 Davis Cup at New Delhi</des>
<color>#262626</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1963</year>
<des>Incumbents

President of India – Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan
Prime Minister of India – Jawaharlal Nehru
Events
Supreme Court of India mandates that reservation should not exceed 50% for any institution.
Hazratbal disappearance episode
Births
28 April - Atul Kumar, Scientist.
29 April - Deepika Chikhalia, actress.</des>
<color>#333333</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1964</year>
<des>27 May - Prime Minister Jawaharlal Nehru dies after a five-month illness; he is succeeded by Lal Bahadur Shastri.
The Vishva Hindu Parishad is founded.
Hazratbal disappearance episode</des>
<color>#404040</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1965</year>
<des>26 January - Hindi becomes the official language of India.
26 January - Anti-Hindi agitations break out in India because of which Hindi does not get "National Language" status and remains one of the 23 Official Languages of India.</des>
<color>#4C4C4C</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1966</year>
<des>3 January - Prime Minister of India Lal Bahadur Shastri and President of Pakistan Ayub Khan sign a Soviet-mediated peace pact in Tashkent, Uzbek S.S.R.
11 January - Prime Minister Shastri dies of heart attack in Tashkent.</des>
<color>#595959</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1967</year>
<des>6 May - Zakir Hussain is the first Muslim to become president of India.
27 May - Naxalite Guerrilla War Beginning with a peasant uprising in the town of Naxalbari, this Marxist/Maoist rebellion sputters on in the Indian countryside. </des>
<color>#666666</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1968</year>
<des>February-The Beatles, Mia Farrow, and several other celebrities visit the ashram of Maharishi Mahesh Yogi in Rishikesh, India. One senior British official frankly admitted that over-assessment “drained the country of its agricultural capital”, </des>
<color>#737373</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1969</year>
<des>Incumbents

President of India – Zakir Hussain until 3 May, V. V. Giri until 20 July (acting president), Mohammad Hidayatullah until 24 August (acting president), V. V. Giri
Prime Minister of India – Indira Gandhi
Events

18 September: Start of the 1969 Gujarat riots
Exact date unknown
The Government of India successfully detonates its first nuclear weapon, outside the country somewhere in USSR, becoming the sixth nation to do so.</des>
<color>#808080</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1970</year>
<des>7 September - Maharashtra Pollution Control Board is established under the provisions of Maharashtra Prevention of Water Pollution Act, 1969.
Bajaj Auto rolls out its 100,000th vehicle.</des>
<color>#8C8C8C</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1971</year>
<des>25 January - Himachal Pradesh becomes the 18th Indian state and East Punjab is reduced to its current form as Doaba.
19 April - The provisional government of Bangladesh exiled flees to West Bengal.</des>
<color>#999999</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1972</year>
<des>21 January - Manipur gets statehood.
19 March - India and Bangladesh sign a friendship treaty, after the withdrawal of the Indian troops.Although the committee’s own interpretation of the riots became widely accepted, modern scholarship has called it into question. </des>
<color>#A6A6A6</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1973
</year>
<des>1 April - Government campaign to save the tiger from extinction.
1 November - Karnataka State is formed.</des>
<color>#B2B2B2</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1974</year>
<des>January to May smallpox epidemic
18 May - Under project Smiling Buddha, India successfully detonates its second nuclear weapon near the Pakistani border, the first time in the country openly becomes the sixth nation to do so.</des>
<color>#BFBFBF</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1975</year>
<des>19 April - The first Indian satellite, Aryabhata, goes into Earth's orbit.
16 May - Sikkim annexed to India after a deposing the monarchy.</des>
<color>#CCCCCC</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1976</year>
<des>The son of then-Prime Minister Indira Gandhi, Sanjay Gandhi, is largely blamed for what turned out to be a failed program.Neil Charlesworth has argued that indebtedness could not have caused the riots. </des>
<color>#D9D9D9</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1977</year>
<des>March - The first non-Congress government sweeps to power following Indira Gandhi's defeat at the general elections. Morarji Desai becomes prime minister.
3 March - Nehru Planetarium commissioned.</des>
<color>#E6E6E6</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1978</year>
<des>1 January - Air India Flight 855, a Boeing 747 passenger jet, crashes into the Arabian Sea after takeoff near Bombay, killing all 213 on board.</des>
<color>#999999</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1979</year>
<des>31 January - The police under direction of Jyoti Basu, Chief Minister of Communist Party of India (Marxist)-led government of West Bengal, surrounds and opens fire on unarmed refugee settlement of Morichjhapi island in Sunderbans, West Bengal. Hundreds killed but government officially accepts 36 deaths.</des>
<color>#666666</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>1980</year>
<des>1 January – Dr. Leo Rebello becomes the Director of Natural Health Centre, Bombay.The riots were aimed at moneylenders, agrees Charlesworth, but this was not a homogeneous group. Money-lenders of the Brahmin caste, and other sowkars indigenous to the area</des>
<color>#0D0D0D</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>1981</year>
<des>July - About 308 people die in Bangalore after drinking illicit liquor (see 1981 Karnataka liquor deaths).
Arasan Ganesan Polytechnic is founded in Sivakasi, Tamilnadu. It is a Government aided co-educational technical institute.</des>
<color>#1A1A1A</color>
</data>

<data>
<year>1982</year>
<des>April - INSAT-1A launched; deactivated in September.
July - NABARD establishment. No one in Britain seemed much aware of the Deccan Riots Commission and the laborious report produced by its members:</des>
<color>#262626</color>
</data>

<data>
<year>1983
</year>
<des>February - Bandit queen Phoolan Devi surrenders.
18 February - Nellie massacre over 2,000 people, mostly Bangladeshi Muslims, were massacred during the Assam agitation.</des>
<color>#333333</color>
</data>

<data>
<year>1984</year>
<des>5 March - Prime Minister of India Indira Gandhi orders Operation Blue Star.
2 April - Squadron Leader Rakesh Sharma is launched into space, aboard the Soyuz T-11.</des>
<color>#404040</color>
</data>

<data>
<year>1985</year>
<des>23 June - Air India Flight 182, a Boeing 747, blows up 31,000 feet (9,500 m) above the Atlantic Ocean, south of Ireland, killing all 329 aboard.
The Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances Act is passed by Parliament.</des>
<color>#4C4C4C</color>
</data>

<data>
<year>1986
</year>
<des>1 April - VSNL incorporated under the Indian Companies Act, 1956.
30 April - Operation Black Thunder conducted to flush out remainin</des>
<color>#595959</color>
</data>

<data>
<year>1987</year>
<des>1 April - VSNL incorporated under the Indian Companies Act, 1956.
30 April - Operation Black Thunder conducted to flush out remainin</des>
<color>#666666</color>
</data>

<data>
<year>1988</year>
<des>The National Consumer Disputes Redressal Commission is set up under the Consumer Protection Act of 1986.
1988 Bihar earthquake</des>
<color>#737373</color>
</data>

<data>
<year>1989</year>
<des>14 February – Union Carbide agrees to pay USD $470 million to the Indian government for damages it caused in the 1984 Bhopal Disaster.
2 December – V.P. Singh becomes the Prime Minister of India after Lok Sabha elections.</des>
<color>#808080</color>
</data>

<data>
<year>1990</year>
<des>January - An insurgency breaks out in Kashmir Valley, inflaming tensions with Pakistan. New Delhi dissolves the state assembly and imposes direct rule.
March - The last Indian troops are withdrawn from Sri Lanka.</des>
<color>#8C8C8C</color>
</data>

<data>
<year>1991
</year>
<des>21 May - Assassination of Rajiv Gandhi Former Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi is assassinated by a LTTE Suicide Bomber in Sriperumbudur near Chennai in Tamil Nadu during the election campaign.</des>
<color>#999999</color>
</data>

<data>
<year>1992</year>
<des>1 February - Chief Judicial Magistrate of Bhopal Court declares Warren Anderson, ex-CEO of Union Carbide, a fugitive under Indian law for failing to appear in the Bhopal Disaster case, and orders the Indian government to press for an extradition from the United States.

</des>
<color>#A6A6A6</color>
</data>

<data>
<year>1993</year>
<des>9 March - The All Parties Hurriyat Conference is formed in Kashmir.
12 March - A series of bomb blasts, thought to be planted by Muslim underworld figures, rock the country's commercial capital of Bombay, killing some 260 people. (See 1993 Mumbai bombings.)</des>
<color>#B2B2B2</color>
</data>

<data>
<year>1994</year>
<des>26 January - India rolls out the short-range Prithvi missile at Republic Day Parade in New Delhi.
20 May - Sushmita Sen was crowned Miss Universe 1994 in Manila, Philippines .
19 November - Aishwarya Rai was crowned Miss World 1994 in Sun City, South Africa .</des>
<color>#BFBFBF</color>
</data>

<data>
<year>1995</year>
<des>5 March - Delhi Metro Rail Corporation Limited founded.[1]
21 September - Reports of the Hindu milk miracle surface.</des>
<color>#CCCCCC</color>
</data>

<data>
<year>1996</year>
<des>January — A major corruption scandal erupts involving allegations that many senior politicians and civil servants have received bribes from prominent businessman Surendra Jain.</des>
<color>#D9D9D9</color>
</data>

<data>
<year>1997</year>
<des>7 February - An alliance of Sikh and Hindu nationalist parties wins a resounding victory over the Congress in state assembly elections in Punjab.
28 February - The government is strengthened by a daring, market friendly budget.</des>
<color>#E6E6E6</color>
</data>

<data>
<year>1998</year>
<des>1 January – The Election Commission announces 16 February as the starting date of the general elections.
11 January – Sonia Gandhi launches her election campaign at Sriperumbudur, where her husband was assassinated.</des>
<color>#404040</color>
</data>

<data>
<year>1999</year>
<des>12 February - The chief minister of Orissa, Janaki Ballabh Patnaik, resigns after pressure within and outside his Congress Party over recent mob attacks on Christians in the state. On 15 February Giridhar Gomango is named to succeed him.</des>
<color>#595959</color>
</data>

<data>
<year>2000</year>
<des>3 January - Prime Minister Atal Bihari Vajpayee accuses Pakistan of being behind the hijacking of an Indian plane and urges that Pakistan be declared a terrorist state.</des>
<color>#0D0D0D</color>
</data>

<data>
<year>2001</year>
<des>1 January - Calcutta officially becomes Kolkata, reverting to its precolonial name.
1 January Dr. Leo Rebello's Encyclopedia of Letters Pen Power and All India Letter Writers Association is entered as a World Record in the Limca Book of Records.</des>
<color>#1A1A1A</color>
</data>



<data>
<year>2002</year>
<des>9 January – The government announces that it is laying landmines along the entire length of its 2,800-km border with Pakistan. One of the committee’s four members was an official from the United Provinces (U.P.), and he could be “expected to support reforms which acknowledged the shortcomings of the principles by which western India had been governed.</des>
<color>#262626</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>2003</year>
<des>26 January - The president of Iran, Mohammad Khatami, is the guest at the Republic Day celebration.
5–9 February - Aero-India show is held in Bangalore.</des>
<color>#333333</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>2004</year>
<des>17 January - The national executive of the Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) meets at Hyderabad.
17 January - P.A. Sangma quits the Nationalist Congress Party and decides to ally with the ruling National Democratic Alliance.</des>
<color>#404040</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>2005</year>
<des>10 January – The Delhi High Court says that a "high claim ratio" cannot be grounds to turn down medical insurance contract renewal requests. The court said that medical policies were liable to be renewed on the same terms and conditions as the old ones.</des>
<color>#4C4C4C</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>2006</year>
<des>2 January – Rajnath Singh assumes office as Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) chief.
7–9 January – Pravasi Bharatiya Divas is organized in Hyderabad.</des>
<color>#595959</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>2007</year>
<des>10 January – India launches four satellites at a time with their PSLV-C7 rocket, including the SRE-1 test article, which will return to Earth in a test for a future Indian manned spaceflight program</des>
<color>#666666</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>2008</year>
<des>2 February - The activists of Maharashtra Navnirman Sena (MNS) try to disrupt a press conference of Samajwadi Party leader Amar Singh in Mumbai.</des>
<color>#737373</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>2009</year>
<des>1 January – 2009 Guwahati bombings Five persons, including a boy and a woman, were killed and about 50 injured in serial bomb blasts in Guwahati, Assam.[1]</des>
<color>#808080</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>2010</year>
<des>2 January - First three Uttar Pradesh rail accidents Three train accidents occur in Uttar Pradesh amid thick fog. Ten people died in the accidents and 45 others were injured.</des>
<color>#8C8C8C</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>2011</year>
<des>Former Telecom Minister A.Raja sent to Tihar Jail in 2G spectrum scam.
Bombay High Court upholds death penalty for Ajmal Kasab.In the event, the committee’s investigation bears far more similarity to the commission than to the committee of inquiry of later years.</des>
<color>#999999</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>2012</year>
<des>3 January President inaugurates new SHAR Mission Control Centre.
9 January 10th Pravasi Bharatiya Divas kicks off in Jaipur. Chief guest – kamala Prasad Bisseasar,Prime Minister of Trinidad and Tobago</des>
<color>#A6A6A6</color>
</data>


<data>
<year>2013</year>
<des>3 January – 7 January 100th Indian Science Congress at Kolkata
6 January India–Pakistan border incidents begin.The Deccan Riots Commission’s affinity to the commissions of previous years becomes all the more evident when we consider that it was invested with the authority</des>
<color>#B2B2B2</color>
</data>
	
</history>
